Jesselyn Radack on Vimeo.mp4
Don't like to put those guys were some words
words I know the media is quick to
do you don't know how whistle blowing
is gas and such a dirty
need of
being people who are out for the
more profit or revenge.
Because all that was somewhere as
I've worked with have
been regular people.
I wouldn't describe them as shrinking violets.
They're usually outspoken
people
who have a good sense of who they are
and their place
in an organization and the limits
of what an organization can
and should be doing.
I think every person in themselves
has a squeel point of
something where it's the they
can no longer endure
witnessing it
now.
I mean on a very basic level
if you see an old lady being mugged.
You probably dial
9 1 1 on your cell phone and
make a police report.
Well that's what some lying.
In my office in the ethics office we
took turns being the duty attorney
for the day and it was
just random that
I happened to be the ethics
officer on desk.
Win I got a call from
the criminal division
of the same Justice
Department saying that
the FBI was on the ground
and wanted to interrogate
an American who is being
called the American
Taliban it was all over the news and
wanted to interrogate him.
And I was told matter of fact
that he had a lawyer.
So in accordance with the advice
we always give in this kind of situation
and
I said you can't do that
he's an American.
He's represented by counsel.
But here are some other ways you can properly
be able to do that.
You could do an undercover.
Oh you could try to get a waiver
I mean there are different that
you could probably do this
in different alternatives to
try to talk to him.
And that was on a Friday.
So the advice
I gave was not unique.
Really.
That case happened to be a high profile
one but this was what
I would normally give to any department
attorney who had an agent
on the ground who wanted to do something.
And this person
who called me called back on
Monday two days later
saying well they
interrogated him anyway despite
your advice the
FBI interrogated the
American Taliban
John Walker Lindh.
What shall we do now and again
I said don't panic.
I mean this happens that people disregard
our advice.
They make an ethical blunder and we
need to help try to fix it so
I said look you can seal
that interview and you can use it for
national security and intelligence
gathering purposes but not
for criminal prosecution.
And they seemed fine with that
answer.
And when they were going to communicate that
to the military
on the ground and the
FBI agent
who had interrogated him.
Then sometime
you know maybe a month or so later
John Ashcroft who was the attorney
general at the time
he was very fond of these very dramatic
press conferences and he gave way
in announcing
that they were
going to charge
John Walker Lindh.
And a reporter
said
I heard he had a lawyer.
Was he able to have his lawyer
with them.
And Ashcroft said if we knew
that he was represented by counsel
he would be allowed to meet with that lawyer.
And I knew there was a flat out lie.
But again he was the attorney general so
it was his prerogative to say what he wanted.
And I kept my mouth shut.
And then a couple of weeks later he
had another press conference
on the same topic.
And by this point
there were pictures circulating
around the world of
John Walker Lindh naked
blindfolded bound to a board
gagged with a butt that's written all
over his head is for head.
And
it looked very reminiscent
of what we've later would see
at Abu Ghraib.
It was clear that he was being
tortured.
And so a reporter asked.
It looks like this guy is being tortured
what's going on.
And again the attorney general said
that his rights had been carefully
scrupulously guarded.
Again I knew that was a complete lie
because they actually commit an
ethics violation and it
sure didn't look like he was
being treated very well.
But again I kept my mouth shut
and they
filed a criminal case against
him which I had advised them
not to do that they did the exact
opposite.
Good thing they're.
Bothering Me. As the case progresses
swears that
it all came down to
a suppression hearing that
he was going to have the crux of the case
was his confession during his interrogation.
The one I hit advised against.
And on
March 7th.
That was a pivotal day for me.
Because the prosecutor himself
e-mailed me and said
as you know there is a federal court
discovery order for all
Justice Department correspondence related
to John Walker and women's interrogation
I have two of your e-mails and
I wanted to make sure
I have everything.
And at that point
I was a laureate because
I knew I had written
WAY more than two e-mails but
I was still
naive about it and
I went up and checked the
hard copy file.
And that's when my heart really sank.
I checked the file
and it was empty except
for two very innocuous pieces of
paper and it had been about an inch
thick.
And at that point
I felt like okay something
really bad is going on.
So I consulted with a senior
attorney who had been a
U.S. attorney for seven years.
And I sat quite
aware what's going on here.
And he just told me you know he
looked through the file and said very matter
of fact we this file has been
purged and
I'm like why is that.
It completely threw me for
a loop because we were simultaneously
prosecuting their interests
in Enron for destruction of evidence
and obstruction of justice and the idea
that the department could actually
get rid of evidence
in violation of a court order no
laugh.
Was unthinkable to me.
At that point
I confronted my boss.
She came in and
I said Claudia
there's a discovery order
and no one told me about it
and apparently it has not been
complied with because a prosecutor
only has to have my e-mails
and she just glared at me
and said very matter of fact
I sent everything
that was in the file.
And at
that point now she's connecting
herself to
death. I mean she is admitting that she
is involved in the
Senate have handled the file.
And
I just said that I wrote more e-mails than
that.
And I didn't quite know what to do
but I knew I didn't want to be a part of us.
I called my husband because he was a
contractor at the time and
I was like look something really
really really unseemly is going
on here and
you need to get a perm a permanent
position because
I think I'm going to resign.
It's that bad like
I don't want to be a part of this
now.
I mean it's if your monumental to me
and
I called up technical
support this is early in the digital
age in its infancy at that apartment.
And I said look
I had all these emails.
You know put them in the trash and
empty my trash on the
computer and they do read
off the computer every
30 days so
I probably can't get them back.
Great.
And they're like oh you know we can get them back nothing
disappears and we spent
hours going through these different ballet
steps to try to recover
them. Then I was able to recover.
About a dozen e-mails of
I know I've written more than
a dozen that had
their documentation and that the
FBI had screwed up and
committed an ethics violation in
its interrogation of
John Walker Lindh.
So I documented the two pieces
of paper in the file and they put in
order all of the other e-mails
and essentially like a bull and about what
they are an attached
Cubbie is word a memo to my
boss to
document that and then a
Xerox copy of it to take
home with me in case the emails
disappeared again
and I
took it to my bath
and she seemed
in a fury that
I had done it.
She's like why wouldn't you send the file.
It's kind of like you
tell me how do you know why weren't they in the file
and
I said you know where
I am not even going to be a part of
whatever game
you're running here.
I am resigning
you have two weeks my two weeks notice in
resigning.
I got a job in another
at a law firm a private law firm.
Doing something totally unrelated to
anything I was trained and
I was doing affordable housing law but
I thought OK socially redeeming
work and a bigger paycheque.
But I continued on the radio
to hear things about the
John Walker Lindh criminal case as
it was progressing
and the things
I was hearing on the radio said to
me
oh John Walker
Lindh never had told full
steam and oh here's raids
were by the book
followed things
I knew were partly untrue and that
told me if my e-mail said and backed
me to the judge
I would think that a person would have the temerity
to be making statements like that
in a weighed very heavily on me
I mean I was a raging insomniac.
I could not fully say
it was I mean the guy had
like three life counts on and
it was a feeling of like you
me and someone could be put to death
because I
I kept my mouth shut
and that
is a really for
me that's the line
I mean that's something
I can live with for me.
So.
You know my moments.
One morning I heard my guests a couple of
then of Newsweek saying
that oh we never had a council that's
not an issue and
I called Make a scarf and
I said I don't know who's tell
you beforehand of bullshit but
I have evidence to prove that it's run.
Before that I had gone to the judge
to try to give him the e-mails but
I no longer worked at the department and
I was told by his clerks
I no longer had standing
by the hand I am I called
Mike
I was just like you keep saying
this and I showed him the e-mails
and he said he would write an article
on it which
he did.
He asked if I wanted to be named
in the article which
I did not act.
He wanted to be anonymous.
So he wrote a really good article that actually
endevour causing
the ultimate collapse of
the John Walker Lindh kith
But meanwhile
Newsweek put up all of my e-mails
with my name on
their new Web site.
So it was like a big red arrow pointing
right at me and
I.
So that really.
Indeed I think by blowing
the whistle I thought it
was over with like
OK
I've done my part.
I can fully began
I can live with myself and whatever
happens happens.
But I didn't realize
I just unleashed the full force
of the entire executive branch
and they came in they saw my new law firm
that I was a criminal that
I would steal new files create
files protected
files and that they should fire me.
They leaned on a private law firm to
fire me which the law firm wouldn't
deal but they put me on this weird
administrative unpeel
indefinite in the mistreated weave.
And
it was like being in purgatory.
Meanwhile you
know they're just describe how can
I hire a lawyer and the
Justice Department starts making noises
about a criminal investigation
and that they were putting me under criminal investigation.
For a forum leaking
which is the first criminal
investigation
I know of since maybe
Ellsberg says.
For someone who did and revealed not
by non-scientific.
I
had done a research memo it during my time
working in the ethics office
I was a world production loss so
I knew what they said and
I knew that
going to the media was an
option and going to
Congress was an option.
I'd already been to my superior
and to the prosecutor saying something
fishy is going on.
I knew that I had you
know I met the standard
I had a reasonable belief
that what I was witnessing evidenced
fraud waste abuse or illegality
or a danger to public health and safety
and so within
that understanding
I blew the whiff of wet
down upon me was that there was a blur
Protection Act is a paper
tiger it has no enforcement
mechanism.
So when the government starts retaliating
against you and big with
there's really nothing you can
do to make it stop.
And the retaliation
began with them trying to get me fired
from my law firm the law firm
being you know playing
both sides of the street cooperating
with the government yet at the same time
claiming I still work there and not
letting me do any work.
And
then you petty
little things like that a lot.
I mean the guy the government actually
helped the law firm.
I. Can test my receipt
of my meagre pathetic unemployment
benefits which
I was entitled to because
I was no longer getting an income.
So I filed for an insurance
and there was pretty
humiliating for me.
But really you're going to can test my you
know big 300 bucks a week
I get to buy gas and groceries
that Peddie though and
as soon as one thing and another would
be again so finally once a criminal
case and did on
September
11. Ironically
of 2003 it ended
with no charges being brought
but within days with the department
had referred me to the state birds of which
I'm licenced as an attorney in both
Maryland and D.C.
So no I had to fight on another front
and all of these fights cost a lot
of money because
I had a private attorney was billing
at a very high rate
upwards of a thousand dollars.
Then I had to have another attorney an employment
attorney dealing with the law firm
which was giving me grief which
kept claiming I was still employed there but
was not paying me
for.
So if it did it was a mess
and the bar referrals.
There was a whole other attorney
I needed for that to deal
with the DC and
Maryland borrowers
A.
The complaint against me in
D.C. lasted until this path
no
10 years before a guard dismissed
and that was only because two of the
major players died.
And then also during that time
I found that I was on the no
fly list on full equity
portion of the no fly list meaning
you get hassled and have to undergo
secondary security screening every
time you fly.
Again that was just in inconvenience
and a way to intimidate and
her wrath and delay
and mess with you.
Basically the government has
a meaning in just
a whole panoply
of things it can do to screw
with the full purse.
LINDH endevour pleading guilty
in a surprise plea bargain
deal on the eve of the
suppression hearing that was going to
bring OUT IN THE OPEN who did what to
whom and who broke
what rules the stuff that
I would boast about.
So it collapsed he pled guilty
to two minor and ministry of infractions
and was.
Over punished with
20 years in jail.
So here again I thought OK end of my ordeal but my ordeal continued for
another.
Three or four years.
And at that point I decided
I was going to dedicate my life to representing
whistleblowers.
Because clearly they were
a group that did not have the protection
that they needed.
I mean my personal experiences
and in
the same time meeting if you are there
with blowers who were going through similar
things and thinking.
OK I want to do this kind of work
because for better or for worse
I've learned it by going very
well. I've gone through.
I've learned was soberer law
so I ended up working for
Alan Grayson who is
Congressman now but at the time
working at his firm little
Rep.. Going after
the people who were blowing the
whistle on reconstruction fraud
in Eye rack and
I did that for two years
so that was sort of poetic justice
if and then.
I mean I was elected to the
D.C. bar and legal ethics committee
so that was more just
ahead of me does
it. No legal ethics there
I understand it that elected
that board and then
an opening.
Alan Garber elected to
Congress an eye
opening occurred
at the Government Accountability
Project to head up a new
national security human
rights program which
was an ideal fit for what
I was doing
I was doing pro bono work
on behalf of clients on a merger
news and writing articles about legal
ethics and
how it meshes with the war on terrorism.
So it was great again.
But I thought
I would be dealing more with kind of the bread
and butter whistleblower cases
where people get
to move to the war they've been
you know that they've had their security
clearance Paul door
and you know it worst maybe
they've been fired.
And there were a number of cases
I didn't like that at first
but then
I read about this guy
Thomas Drake and
everything I read described
him a behaviour as a whistleblower.
It described exactly what
I was familiar with do you
any good and
I did.
And at that point no new we had crossed the
Rubicon into
a new age.
If we were going to criminally prosecute
whistleblowers and do so for espionage
a law meant to go after spies
not with the blowers
and so my practice
has developed
into you representing
unfortunately a long list of people
right now who've been charged who
have been investigated
or charged under
the Espionage Act.
The Espionage
Act is this long into quid
overbroad extremely
The fact
that
I mean when it was written in
it even though that's
decades before the word classified
even into the lexicon.
So they're talking about war materials
and designs
and films and
you know it was completely.
Antiquated but really it was meant to go
after spies and
not people
who were trying to do the right thing so
the fact that that was being used was a very
heavy handed and very dangerous.
Certainly concerned me
and I definitely worried about the fact
that this happened to
Tom I was hoping it was just
a serious one off
and then it wouldn't happen again but
now it's happened seven or eight times.
But because of my experience with time
I continue to represent other
whistleblowers who have been charged under
the Espionage
Act and continue
Did you so today.
By insisting in the
production
of an enforcement mechanism
I would say jury trials.
And jury trials
so people can see where it goes until
now and these are all in ministry
they have a process
for quite
a real.
My suggestion.